don't go up so fast that wasn't bad but
don't go up so fast you take the ball
what did i do too you went here too fast
so you're gonna come what one two
toss and then go
the arm come down all the way watch here
here let the arm come down down toss
and then hit
higher
do you know what i mean by in front but
when you throw it behind you won't be
able to rotate into the serve because i
want you to start developing some surf
power and you got to utilize your body
in a certain way so if you don't throw
it in front
you're going to miss out on the torso
rotation on this you're going to be
sideways and hitting the ball
here like this so i want you to do is
throw it in front a little bit
and then you're going to rotate into it
like this this
see as soon as the racket drops you
start coming you start coming this way
with the shoulders
and this little action gives you more
power on the surface so you're gonna go
here
here toss in front and rotate into it
like that
better do this with me now when we throw
it in front we're going to go
towards the left pocket watch we're
going towards the left pocket
there you go see that this side is going
to come down a little bit because of
that okay so it's a downward
forward rotation
there you go and see how the weight
shifts onto the front foot now if you
want to lift the back foot up in the air
that's fine
but that's the rotation it's going to
give you a lot of momentum it's going to
give you a lot more power
it's going to make the swing a lot
easier more effortless
there it is and see how you when you
finish like this this is a good sign
yeah a very good sign oh when i toss
do i stand on this line no that's a good
question so remember our last
third lesson we we said we're going to
count right so we're going to go one
two is going to be here on the back foot
three is going to be toss and go forward
so when you toss you start going forward
again okay so you're gonna go
one here you're gonna go two
lag back foot and now three forward
like that okay so it's kind of like
simultaneously
returning your center of gravity from
right
absolutely you're starting to go forward
now we're going to add something else
later we're going to get on the toes and
bend the knees and go even more forward
but let's start
with this rotation only we're going to
add the other stuff later okay
not bad but throw the ball a little bit
higher yeah see when you throw it in
front naturally you kind of
rotate forward you see that very nice
better
much better what do you think
very nice so once you start identifying
when it's bad yes
when you're by yourself without me
looking at you you can you want to start
feeling if it's behind you and then
on the next time you serve you correct
it and try to get it more in front
more in front that wasn't far enough in
front do it again
that was a really really nice serve so
let's add something else to sir because
today we're building a little bit more
power into your serve okay so now what i
want you to do is get on your toes
i want you to practice by me holding
your racket put your rack in a trophy
position
and i try to get on your toes and also
bend your knees a little bit
now don't get on the toes like ballet
more on the balls of your feet i would
say if you look at the foot
it's going to be somewhere here yeah
there it's not going to be towards the
tip okay
yeah yeah so doing it there and i'll
bend your knees a little bit bend bend
your knees
a little bit more when you get the
racket to about this position i want you
to
be in this exact position with your body
knees
slightly bent like this and then on the
toes like that
and now when you throw it in front
naturally you want to lean forward a
little bit
towards the ball that's in front so let
me show you that go ahead and hold the
rack in the trophy
go ahead get on your toes okay bend your
knees a little bit
and i'll lean forward i'm going to hold
you lean there you go there you go
my body weight is on the left foot
exactly you feel it on the left foot
yes yes when you lean forward naturally
it's going to go towards the left foot
and now when you accelerate go lean a
little more lean
lean more see how you're losing balance
yes so that's what's going to happen on
the serve so that's how we're going to
build the power in the serve so we
already are rotating we're already doing
that we're going towards the left pocket
so now also we're going to go toss it in
front get on our toes
and then we go forward like that okay
let's try it out
get on your toes more that's not bad but
get on your toes we just talked about
watch yeah watch me again one two
three toes and knees
better
okay now what i want you to do is when
you go upwards
okay allow the body to go don't hold
yourself on the ground
if i go fast here and i accelerate up
first you see my body goes up towards
the ball
naturally so accelerate up
towards that ball
allow the body to go up it's not bad i
like the rotation
you didn't go forward much i want you to
do two things now in addition to
rotating i want you to go
forward and also up like this towards
the ball that's up
and in front of you okay do it again
there you go oh my goodness you saw that
by the way i want you to not get
frustrated with the toss because the
toss
is very complex yeah because you're
doing two separate things with the
hitting arm at the non-heading arm
and also you're doing many other things
with the body so the toss even at the
professional level at the elite level
there's even some players
at that level believe it or not that
have trouble with the toss so that's how
complex it is yes the toss is always a
very difficult thing so don't be too
hard on yourself
if you're not getting it right like if
you get out of 10
tosses if maybe three or four are good
right now that's not bad
it's okay to not toss it perfect every
time it's all right
okay it was a little too far in front do
it again
okay it's good i like what you're doing
there you're doing the thing we learned
in the beginning the rotation you're
rotating much better
you are throwing the ball more in front
there was a nice serve but let's try to
add a little
more and we got to add the knee bends
and getting on your toes
because you're a visual learner i'm
going to show you one more time all
right now
watch exactly what's going to happen to
my body as my racket starts to travel up
towards the trophy position
so here i'm gonna do your rhythm okay
one
and i will go two okay three
you see what i did yeah you go here
here here here you see this toes and
knees
toes and knees and the balls in front
i'm going to also lean a little bit
and at the same time i'm also
accelerating so that's what you got to
add to your serve okay
more in front and
okay remember we there was one time we
played on the wall i made you aware of
something that you're doing sometimes
is that you bend too early so if you're
going here
here and now if you bend here it's too
early because now you're going to bend
and toss at the same time
very common mistake so always bend
without always excuse me always toss
without bending the knees
it's unnecessary because what will
happen is you'll bend to toss the ball
and then you'll straighten it and you'll
bend again
so you do like a double knee bend so so
wait the bend
until the ball is already in the air all
right
it was behind you exactly i know it's
a tough day today but it was pretty good
try
okay if you wait for the ball to drop to
here you don't get no vertical momentum
you understand what i'm saying you have
to strike the ball much higher
if you allow the ball to come down to
this you will not get vertical momentum
exactly so for the rotational horizontal
momentum you're getting because now
you're freely rotating
and you're fixing your toss so you're
adding one power source your server is
already harder and more powerful because
of that if you want to get an additional
power source
which is a vertical momentum upward
momentum you have to allow
the contact to be higher and allow the
body to go up towards that higher
contact
don't hold yourself down and wait until
the ball drops too low
okay
yeah you know what you did right your
hand is still kind of extended well of
course
and i i don't do it you know what that
is i think it's leverage that
see that's one thing that is going to
help you get vertical momentum is if you
continue
staying up with this toss arm it's going
to put your shoulder
tilted and then when you accelerate
upwards you're going to reverse this
tilt
it's going to help you go up even more
okay do it again
keep going
that was the old serve where it was
behind you that was without any it was
pretty much all arm right
so you went like this no rotation
then it was all armed
better better
better way better
don't bend twice don't bend twice come
on wait
one two three
okay do it again
better i like it a lot better i got
exercise for you here let me have your
racket
and now you're gonna high-five me up
here right after my hand throughout the
whole service motion there you go do it
again go after my hand
do it again there you go one more time
not too hard okay there you go all right
you seen
you see now one more time okay sure
this is really helpful okay good do it
again
there you go now you're doing it see how
you see now how you're getting that
vertical momentum
you're allowing the body to go up okay
you're accelerating upwards
that's exactly what you need to do on
your server sure you need to understand
all right here we go
one two
three there you go
do that that's exactly what you should
do on the serve one
two three high five
i can't even believe you attempted to
hit that one that was like a multiple
football
there was three footballs in one you
would jog towards the ball
yeah not bad not bad do it again but you
you're not leaning though
remember you got to lean lean on this
foot here lean here
like that so when you finish you finish
on your left foot
yes that was it
wow okay do it again one more time
yes better do it again
here you know what the fascinating thing
about
this what i'm teaching you is what i
call the passive leg drive
so passive leg drive so now what happens
is because you're doing all these things
correct you're doing the
the shoulder of a shoulder you're
throwing the ball in front you're
leaning forward more
you're bending your knees you're getting
on your toes when you accelerate upwards
towards the ball
your body is lifting off the ground so
you're not actually consciously jumping
but the legs are being propelled off the
ground by your body
there it is you're doing it now every
time
that was a nice one there if you allow
the body to meet the ball
very high because you notice how in the
beginning you were kind of making
contact here and you were kind of
holding yourself down yeah
so if you allow the body to make contact
much higher
with a full extension with the whole
body stretching towards the ball when
you were like you when you were
high-fiving me remember
and in addition to that if you throw the
ball a little bit in front it'll make
you land inside the cord
yeah and now again like i said before
you're rotating much better
so how do you prevent that remember how
do you prevent not rotating into it
what causes that remember not rotating
yeah if you don't rotate if you make
contact back here what will cause that
bad toss right so if you throw it back
here you won't be able to rotate into it
it's
completely an arm movement so now when
you start throwing in front you're
allowing your torso to rotate forward
that's horizontal momentum you're doing
it much better it's going to give you
additional power
and if you can add what we did second
the vertical momentum you're going to
also add
a second source of power to the server
which is the vertical momentum
right and you combine those two together
you combine the horizontal and the
vertical momentum
you're adding a lot of effortless power
to your serve you can see the serves are
going much harder
yeah but again the most important thing
is the toss and it requires a lot of
practice
so be patient but good job good job
today
all right nice job